PERSONAL INFORMATION

# Carlos Gómez Guijarro

x cgzguijarro@gmail.com

Date of birth 26th Dec. 1990 | Nationality Spanish

# RESERCH PROFILE

WORK EXPEDIENCE

My scientific interest is to discover our cosmic origins by exploring the formation and evolution of the structures in our Universe. In my research I use both detailed and statistical studies of galaxy samples and multiwavelength datasets ranging from X-ray to radio, being PI and Co-I of numerous observing time proposals. I always envision my research with a local and an international scope, collaborating with both small teams and big international collaborations. I am very active in transmitting my results in international conferences and my knowledge by supervising students.

WORK EXPERIENCE	
2019/10-current	CNRS postdoctoral researcher at UMR AIM (DAp) - CEA Paris-Saclay
2015/10–2019/09	PhD Fellow at Cosmic Dawn Center, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Prior 2018/07 PhD Fellow at Dark Cosmology Centre, Niels Bohr Institute
2017/04–06	Visiting intern at Cornell University, USA
2013/02-2015/09	Research assistant at UCM, Spain
2015/07	Visiting intern at IRyA, Mexico
2014/07–09	Research intern at IAC, Spain
EDUCATION	
2015/10–2019/09	PhD in Astrophysics, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Denmark
	PhD degree awarded on May 15, 2019  Thesis: Connecting the Extremes - High-redshift Starbursts as Progenitors of Massive Galaxies
2013/10–2014/09	
2013/10-2014/09	Master of Science in Astrophysics, Universidad Complutense Madrid, Spain  Average grade: 9.0/10 – Thesis: 9.2/10 - Distinction in the course <i>Galaxy Formation and Evolution</i>
2008/10–2013/09	Bachelor of Science in Physics and Astrophysics, Universidad Complutense Madrid, Spain Long cycle degree of 5 years - Top 10% of the class - Awarded with 12 distinctions – Access grade: 9.23/10
COLLABORATIONS	
International teams and projects	
2023–	ALMA-FPA development study (co-l)
2022–	Public Release Imaging for Extragalactic Research (JWST), PRIMER (member)
2022–	The Cosmic Evolution Early Release Science Survey (JWST), CEERS (member)
2019–	GOODS-ALMA, 1.1mm galaxy survey (data manager)
2018–	BUFFALO, a HST survey in the Frontier Fields (member)
2015–	The Cosmic Evolution Survey, COSMOS (member)
2015–	SHARDS, an ESO/Gran Telescopio Canarias large program in GOODS-N and the Frontier Fields (member)
International collaborations	
	CEA Saclay/LAM (France), DAWN/DARK (Denmark), ESO (Germany), NOIRLab/Stanford University/NASA

# PUBLICATION SUMMARY

(as of 30<sup>th</sup> September 2024)

• 8 first-author publications in peer-reviewed journals with 304 citations

Ames/Cornell University (USA), IRyA (Mexico), CAB/IAC/UCM (Spain)

- 65 publications in peer-reviewed journals with 2405 citations
- H-index: 29

# SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

2015/10-2019/09

PhD Fellowship, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Denmark

2014/07-2014/09

Summer Grant at the IAC within the Program of Initiation to Astrophysical Research

2013-2014

Collaboration Scholarship by the Ministry of Education of the Spanish Government

Awarded to talented students to collaborate with a university department

2008-2009

Scholarship for Outstanding Students by the Education Office of the Community of Madrid Awarded to students with the top grades at the Spanish University Access Test

#### **KEY PRACTICAL SKILLS**

### Data reduction

- Processing of optical/near-IR imaging drizzled data (JWST, HST)
- Calibration and imaging of (sub)mm/radio interferometric data (ALMA, VLA)
- Processing of optical/near-IR spectroscopy (Keck/MOSFIRE, NOT/ALFOSC and FIES)
- Processing of X-ray imaging data (Chandra)

# Data analysis

- Development of an aperture photometry code
- Development of an interferometric uv-plane stacking code
- Analysis of optical/near-IR and sub(mm)/radio imaging and spectra
- Source detection, photometry, and catalog build-up of optical/near-IR (SExtractor, aperture and model fitting photometry) and (sub)mm/radio (PyBDSF, photometry in image and uv-plane) data
- SED fitting of optical/near-IR (EAZY, FAST, LePhare) and far-IR/panchromatic (CIGALE) data
- · Morphological fitting of optical/near-IR (GALFIT, Stattmorph) and (sub)mm/radio (CASA, GILDAS) data
- Machine Learning techniques (CNN, Random forests)

#### Computing

- Programming: Python, R, C/C++, MATLAB Mathematics: Maple, Mathematica
- Operating systems: Linux, Mac, Windows Office automation: LaTeX, MS Office

# Languages

- Spanish: Mother tonque
- English: Full working proficiency (C2)
- French: Professional working proficiency (C1)

# OBSERVING TIME ALLOCATION AND EXPERIENCE

### Proposal time allocation

#### Optical/near-IR:

PI – ESO/KMOS 112.25EX (2h B - Resub): Instantaneous star formation rate to uncover the role of compact star formation

PI - ESO/KMOS 110.23UN (8h B grade): Instantaneous star formation rate to uncover the role of compact star formation

Co-I – JWST-GO-05572 (16.8h): Red Monsters: Kinematics of Two 'Universe Breaking', Ultra-Massive Galaxies in the First Gyı

Co-I – JWST-GO-05019 (4.7h): The prevalence of TP-AGB stars in the near-IR rest-frame spectra of high redshift quenched galaxies: implications for spectral synthesis models and galaxy evolution

Co-I – JWST-GO-03567 (47.6h): A deep dive into the physics of the first massive quiescent galaxies in the Universe

 $\label{eq:collinear} \text{Co-I} - \text{ESO/X-Shooter 112.25C4 (53h A} - \textit{Resub}) : \text{Deep spectroscopy of bright red massive quiescent galaxies at z} \sim 2.5 - 3$ 

Co-I-ESO/FORS2 112.25JF (6h B grade): Unveiling Mpc-scale structure of a maturing protocluster at z = 3.61

Co-I – ESO/KMOS 111.24JS (31h B grade - Resub): The gas content of sub-millimeter compact galaxies at cosmic noon

Co-I – ESO/KMOS 110.240K (21.3h B grade): Uncovering the role of optically dark galaxies in an overdensity at z = 3.5

Co-I - ESO/X-Shooter 109.22Y5 (56h A grade): Deep spectroscopy of bright red massive quiescent galaxies at z  $\sim$  2.5 - 3 Co-I - ESO/KMOS 109.23CE (31h B grade): The gas content of sub-millimeter compact galaxies at cosmic noon

Co-I – Keck/MOSFIRE S22A-046 (2nights): The emerge of the first quiescent galaxies – take 2

Co-I – Gemini/GMOS 21BCF05 (9.8h): Are submm compact main sequence galaxies actually faded starbursts?

Co-I – Keck/MOSFIRE S20B-031 (2nights): The emerge of the first quiescent galaxies

Co-I – Keck/MOSFIRE S20A-037 (1nights): Direct spectroscopic confirmation of z > 4 quiescent galaxies

Co-I – Keck/MOSFIRE S18B-040 (1nights): Direct spectroscopic confirmation of z > 4 quiescent galaxies

Co-I - HST GO 15117 (101orbits): BUFFALO

Co-I – Keck/MOSFIRE S17B-106 (1nights): Direct spectroscopic confirmation of z > 4 guiescent galaxies

# (Sub)mm/radio:

PI - NOEMA W23CU (6h A grade): Dead or alive? Az = 4.106 quiescent galaxy with slow outflows

PI – VLA 22B-243 (13.2h B grade): The true extent of the cold gas content in a red sequence progenitor

PI – NOEMA W21CO (8h B grade): Uncovering a unique population of gas giants at z = 1.2

PI – NOEMA W19CV (7.3h B grade): Peering into the pace of massive galaxy evolution

Co-I – ALMA 2024.1.01744.S (38.5h C grade): ALMA+JWST: studying the efficient formation of massive galaxies at zspec=3-5

# Page 2 / 5

Co-I – ALMA 2023.1.00652.S (6.5h C grade): Unveiling the Mpc-scale structure of a maturing protocluster at z = 3.61 Co-I – ALMA 2023.1.00180.L (143.5h A grade): The COSMOS High-z ALMA-MIRI Population Survey (CHAMPS): A Wide-Area Comprehensive Survey of the Dusty Universe Co-I - ALMA 2023.1.00170.S (6.7h B grade): Caught in the Web: ALMA Data for Every Sub-Millimeter Galaxy Over the COSMOS-Web Survey Field Co-I - NOEMA S23CT (5.4h A grade): CII follow-up for a dusty star-forming galaxy at z=6.09 Co-I – NOEMA S23CY (12h A grade): Revealing the interstellar medium of two extremely massive galaxies at z > 7 Co-I - NOEMA W22DA (14h B grade): JWST and NOEMA unveil the nature of submm-compact galaxies Co-I – VLA 22B-124 (67.1h B grade): A golden reference for ISM studies of distant normal galaxies: completion Co-I – ALMA 2022.1.00884.S (8.7h A grade): Redshift scans for dusty star-forming galaxies at cosmic dawn Co-I - NOEMA S22CN (20h A grade): Optically-dark galaxies in the EGS field Co-I - VLA 22A-400 (60h B grade): High redshift star formation and AGN activity in the JWST CEERS public survey Co-I – NOEMA M21AA (159h A grade): NOEMA forming-clusters evolution survey (NICE) Co-I - VLA 21B-292 (60h C grade): High redshift star formation and AGN activity in the JWST CEERS public survey Co-I – ALMA 2021.1.00815.S (39.8h C grade): Testing structure formation, quenching and gas accretion models Co-I - VLA 21A-133 (165.5h B grade): A golden reference for ISM studies of distant normal galaxies Co-I - VLA 21A-043 (11.5h C - Resubmission): Flares, breaks and warps in the outskirts of the HI and stellar disk of UGC11859 Co-I – VLA 20B-247 (24.2h C grade): Investigating possible non-gravitational ICM heating in a galaxy cluster at z = 2 Co-I - VLA 20A-485 (9h C grade): Flares, breaks and warps in the outskirts of the HI and stellar disk of UGC11859 Co-I – NOEMA 225-19 (22h B grade): Knocking on giant's door: A large-scale view of candidate z > 4 dusty galaxies Co-I – ALMA 2018.1.01676.S (9.4h C grade): A total mass profile for a prototypical z ~ 4.6 massive star forming disk galaxy Co-I – ALMA 2018.1.01225.S (19.4h C - Resubmission): What is the origin and subsequent evolution of starbursts at z ~ 2? Co-I – ALMA 2016.1.01001.S (14.6h C grade): What is the origin and subsequent evolution of starbursts at z ~ 2? Gran Telescopio Canarias 10.4m (OSIRIS, 1night); Keck 10m (MOSFIRE, 2half-nights); Nordic Optical Visitor observations Telescope 2.6m (ALFOSC and FIES, 8nights); Calar Alto Observatory 2.2m (CAFOS and FOCES, 3nights) **CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS** Invited talks Participation through personal invitation: 2024/06 Cosmic Odysseys 2024: The Interstellar Medium of Galaxies and AGN since Cosmic Dawn 2024/04 Dust in Trieste: Bridging the observations and models of dust in early galaxies in the JWST era 2023/06 French Society of Astronomy Meeting 2023, Strasbourg, France 2023/03 The growth of galaxies in the early universe VIII, Sexten, Italy 2022/11 BOBAFET (transdisciplinary SFH workshop), LAM, Marseille, France 2022/03 The growth of galaxies in the early universe VII, Sexten, Italy 2021/11 Sino-French workshop: Simulations and observations of galaxies and protoclusters, Nanjing (Virtual), China 2021/10 High-z dusty galaxies, LAM, Marseille, France 2020/01 The growth of galaxies in the early universe VI, Sexten, Italy 2018/03 Galaxy interactions and mergers across cosmic time, Sexten, Italy 2017/11 The physics of quenching massive galaxies at high redshift, Leiden, The Netherlands Contributed talks Participation through abstract review: 2023/11 Resolving the extragalactic universe with ALMA and JWST, Tokyo, Japan 2023/07 GECO conference - Shedding new light on the first billion year of the Universe, Marseille, France 2022/06 EAS 2022 - The main sequence: going beyond the scaling relation, Valencia, Spain 2022/06 EAS 2022 - The ISM of infrared galaxies from present to cosmic noon, Valencia, Spain 2022/03 Cosmic nuggets: A feast of compact and massive galaxies across the universe, Sexten, Italy 2020/03 IAU Symposium 359: Galaxy evolution and feedback across different environments, Bento Gonçalves, Brazil 2018/09 Birth, life and fate of massive galaxies and their central beating heart, Favignana, Italy 2018/08 IAU GA 2018 – Division J Meeting – Build-up of galaxy clusters, Vienna, Austria Spanish Society of Astronomy Meeting 2018, Salamanca, Spain 2018/07 2014/09 Spanish Society of Astronomy Meeting 2014, Teruel, Spain Team meeting talks Participation through team membership:

Co-I – ALMA 2023.1.01571.S (36.4h C grade): On the formation of cosmic DUNES: The first dusty galaxies of the universe Co-I – ALMA 2023.1.00837.S (1h A grade): Hidden in plain sight: dynamical mass estimates for a newly-discovered red

monster at zspec~5.6 in the GOODS-S field

2023/05

2022/07

CEERS Team Meeting 2023, Austin, USA

COSMOS Team Meeting 2022, Paris, France

ASPECS Team Meeting 2019, Schloss Ringberg, Germanv 2019/11 2019/09 GOODS-ALMA Meeting 2019, CEA Saclay, France 2018/06 COSMOS Team Meeting 2018, Copenhagen, Denmark 2017/07 COSMOS Team Meeting 2017, Kvoto, Japan COSMOS Team Meeting 2016, Baltimore, USA 2016/06 **Posters** Participation through abstract review: 2023/07 EAS 2023 - Coming out of darkness: how JWST is changing our view of high-z dusty galaxies, Kraków, Poland 2021/06 EAS 2021, Leiden (Virtual), The Netherlands 2017/08 SMG20, Durham, UK 2014/06 EWASS 2015 – Galaxy studies in the mid-infrared form space and ground. Tenerife, Spain COLLOQUIA. SEMINARS, AND TALKS Colloquia series Through abstract review: 2022/03 Hypatia Colloquium 2022, ESO Garching, Germany Invited talks Through personal invitation: 2023/05 Space Science & Astrobiology Division seminars, NASA Ames, California, USA 2023/05 KIPAC Cosmology seminars, Stanford University, California, USA 2022/02 Department of Astronomy seminars, Stockholm University, Sweden 2021/12 Joint ALMA Observatory colloquia, Santiago, Chile 2021/05 CAB MdM seminars, Centro de Astrobiología, Madrid, Spain 2021/03 IPARCOS astro-seminars, Universidad Complutense, Madrid, Spain 2019/11 Journal club seminars, IAP, Paris, France Visitor talks During a scientific visit: 2023/12 Café club, LAM, Marseille, France 2022/11 Cake talks, DAWN, Copenhagen, Denmark 2017/11 Subaru seminars, Subaru Telescope, Hawaii, USA 2017/11 Freddie seminars, IfA, Hawaii, USA 2016/04 Advanced radio astronomy seminars, Cornell University, USA Local talks As a local scientist: 2023/06 DAp postdocs seminars, CEA Saclay, France 2020/05 LCEG DAp seminars, CEA Saclay, France 2019/05 Interferometry seminar, DARK, Copenhagen, Denmark 2018/03 Cake talks, DARK, Copenhagen, Denmark STUDENT SUPERVISION 2022/10-Maxime Tarrasse, PhD student, CEA Saclay, France - Co-supervisor (50%) 2021/10-David Blánquez Sesé, PhD student, DAWN - DTU, Copenhagen, Denmark - Co-supervisor (50%) 2022/11-Rosa Maria Mérida, PhD student, CAB, Spain - Project supervisor (100% on specific PhD thesis project) 2019/10-2022/12 Mengyuan Xiao, PhD student, CEA Saclay/Nanjing University, France/China - Co-supervisor (50%) 2021/01-06 Guillaume Villaret, Master student (M1), CEA Saclay, France - Main supervisor (100%) 2020/01-06 David Blánquez Sesé, Master student, DAWN - DTU, Copenhagen, Denmark - Co-supervisor (33%) 2022/04-06 Victor Jaulin, Bachelor student (L3), CEA Saclay, France – Main supervisor (100%) **TEACHING EXPERIENCE** University of Copenhagen (280h over three courses): Teaching assistant 2018 Danish Summer School in observational astronomy (Master level course)

2017–2018

Cosmology (3<sup>rd</sup> year physics bachelor course)

**PROFESSIONAL SERVICE** Organization of scientific meetings 2023/07 EAS 2023 Symposium - Early assembly of galaxies with JWST spatially resolved spectroscopy and photometry (SOC), Krakow, Poland 2018/06 COSMOS Team Meeting 2018 (LOC), Copenhagen, Denmark Reviewer 2023 PhD thesis external referee - Ángela García Argumánez (UCM, Spain) 2019-Referee for ApJ, A&A, and MNRAS 2022-2023 Evaluation of ESO Period 110, 112 proposals 2021-2023 Evaluation of ALMA Cycle 8, 9, 10, 11 proposals 2018 Evaluation of a Gemini telescope proposal on behalf of the Canadian Time Allocation Committee Others 2020-Organization team member of the astrophysics seminars of the DAp, CEA Saclay, France 2018 Creator, organizer and speaker of the seminar series All you always wanted to know about, aimed at discussing and sharing knowledge about general astronomy topics, DARK, Copenhagen, Denmark **OUTREACH** 2019/12 Interview for the podcast Hablando con Científicos of cienciaes.com, Madrid, Spain Exhibiter at the event Art in Science during the Culture Night 2018, Copenhagen, Denmark 2018/10 As winner of the Mega category in the 2017 contest 2017/10 Exhibiter at the event Art in Science during the Culture Night 2017, Copenhagen, Denmark 2013/03 Volunteer at La Uni en la Calle (2nd edition), Madrid, Spain 2012/11 Volunteer at La Uni en la Calle (1st edition), Madrid, Spain 2009/11 Volunteer at the IX Week of Science, Madrid, Spain

Niels Bohr Institute Summer School in observational astronomy (Master level course)

**REFERENCES** 

2016

Prof. Sune Toft DAWN - U. Copenhagen, Denmark sune@nbi.ku.dk Dr. David Elbaz CEA Saclay, France david.elbaz@cea.fr Prof. Georgios Magdis DAWN - DTU, Denmark geoma@space.dtu.dk Dr. Emanuele Daddi CEA Saclay, France edaddi@cea.fr Dr. Laure Ciesla laure.ciesla@lam.fr LAM, France Prof. Dominik Riechers University of Cologne, Germany riechers@ph1.uni-koeln.de Prof. Pablo G. Pérez-González CAB, Spain pgperez@cab.inta-csic.es Dr. Mark Dickinson NSF's NOIRLab, USA mark.dickinson@noirlab.edu Dr. Natascha M. Föster Schreiber MPE Garching, Germany forster@mpe.mpg.de